A Guide to the Robert B. Carper Collection
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Robert B. Carper Collection 1820-1862
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
83/Jun/09
.25 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Dr. William Bean from his family files.
Biographical/Historical Information
Robert Benjamin Carper was born in Greenbrier, Virginia in 23 Nov. 1836. Second of seven children, Carper graduated from the Medical College of Virginia in 1861. While a doctor he could have joined the Army as an officer, but he refused a commission and joined the 11th Virginia Volunteers, known as the Fincastle Rifles, as an infantryman to be with his two brothers. After a one year enlistment, and in poor health, he reenlisted to stay with his brothers.
Carper was injured in the Battle of Williamsburg on 5 May, 1862 and was sent to a hospital in Williamsburg where he died two weeks later on 19 May. He is buried in Williamsburg with his mother's family.
Scope and Content
The collection includes several personal items received when Carper was a student at MCV and that he used while in the Confederate Army.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in chronological order
Contents List
- Books 1820, 1855 (Box-folder 1)
  - Military Laws 1820 (Box-folder 1a)
    By C. W. Gooch. There is a stamp of "B. Carper" on the front page. This book was a compilation of military laws, military medical and general knowledge involving the US Army of that time period. Printed by the Adjunct General's Office of Virginia.
  - A Pocket Formulary and Physician's Manual 1855, The cover is worn and it looks like the closing flap has been re-sewn. (Box-folder 1b)
    By Thomas S. Powell, MD. The book has markings in the section on medical ethics. It is an example of books at this time for field medical reference. It contains recipes and instructions.
  - Notebook written by Carper and his family after him. (Box-folder 1c)
    This notebook contains lecture notes from MCV, family obituaries, pressed flowers, and other mementoes of their life. The obituary for Robert Carper is incorrect as it is listing his death in 1861, when he died in 1862.
- Medical Lecture Tickets, Medical College of Virginia 1859-1861 (Box-folder 2)
  This series contains the following tickets. Each was an entry into the lecture as was the custom at the time. This practice decreased as class sizes changed. Each ticket admits Robert Carper to the lecture and is signed on the back by the instructor.
  - Midwifery & Diseases of Women and Children 1859-1860, 1860-1861 (Box-folder 2a)
    Dr James H. Conway, Professor.
  - Surgery and Surgical Anatomy 1859-1860 (Box-folder 2b)
    Dr. Charles Bell Gordon, Professor.
  - Institutes of Medicine 1860-1861 (Box-folder 2c)
    Dr. L.S. Joynes, Professor
- Daguerreotype and Photographs (Box-folder 3)
  This series contains a daguerreotype of Robert Carper in a wooden sided, bronze framed picture box. It has a bronze clasp and detailed woodworking on the box. There are also two photographs of the daguerreotype as well.
- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 4)
  This series contains a locket of Carper's hair, wrapped in a piece of tissue.